<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on claudia.reyes@anu.edu.au</title>
    <link>https://claudiarreyes.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on claudia.reyes@anu.edu.au</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 08:57:33 +1100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://claudiarreyes.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic modes in M67 trace deepening convective envelopes</title>
      <link>https://claudiarreyes.github.io/post/small_spacings/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 08:57:33 +1100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://claudiarreyes.github.io/post/small_spacings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!--&#xA;Stars constantly vibrate with acoustic waves that travel through their interiors. These vibrations carry detailed information about the physical structure hidden beneath a star’s surface. By studying the frequency patterns of these oscillations, we can measure things like a star’s density and even estimate its age.&#xA;&#xA;Two types of frequency differences are particularly important: large separations, which are sensitive to the average density of the star, and small separations, which are linked to the structure of the stellar core. In main-sequence stars like the Sun, small separations provide a powerful window into the core’s properties and can be used to estimate stellar ages.&#xA;&#xA;It has long been thought that once stars evolve beyond the main sequence—becoming subgiants and eventually red giants—small separations lose much of their diagnostic power, simply scaling with the large ones.&#xA;&#xA;Our recent study challenges that assumption.&#xA;&#xA;Using asteroseismic data from 27 stars in the open cluster M67, we found clear deviations from this expected scaling. We observed that changes in the slope of the small frequency separations correspond to changes in the structure of the nuclear fusion regions.&#xA;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; flex-wrap: wrap; justify-content: center; gap: 2rem; padding: 2rem 0;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;video style=&#34;flex: 1 1 300px; max-width: 40%;&#34; controls&gt;&#xA;    &lt;source src=&#34;https://claudiarreyes.github.io/videos/small_separations_1.0M.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;&#xA;    Your browser does not support the video tag.&#xA;  &lt;/video&gt;&#xA;&#xA;  &lt;video style=&#34;flex: 1 1 300px; max-width: 40%;&#34; controls&gt;&#xA;    &lt;source src=&#34;https://claudiarreyes.github.io/videos/small_separations_1.7M.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;&#xA;    Your browser does not support the video tag.&#xA;  &lt;/video&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&#xA;  &lt;figcaption style=&#34;font-size: 0.8em; color: gray;&#34;&gt;Tracks of solar metallicity show that the small separations (CD diagram) follow the structure of the nuclear fusion regions, highlighted in red in both the polar and Kippenhahn diagrams (indicating zones where nuclear burning exceeds 10 erg g&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; s&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;). The dotted regions represent the convective envelope. Letters mark key transition points. At each point, the age of the track is presented, and below, a descriptive label for the current evolutionary stage.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;However there is one feature in the sequence, &#34;the plateau&#34; (occurring on the lower red giant branch), which is unrelated to the fusion regions.&#xA;&#xA;As stars evolve, their outer convective layers begin to dig deeper into the interior. When the base of the convective envelope reaches a sensitive region inside the star, it leaves a noticeable imprint on the small separations: the &#34;plateau&#34; —an effect we clearly detect in the observational data from M67.&#xA;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; justify-content: center; padding: 2rem 0;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;video style=&#34;width: 100%; max-width: 800px; border-radius: 8px;&#34; controls&gt;&#xA;    &lt;source src=&#34;https://claudiarreyes.github.io/videos/animation_with_audio_models_only_no_jargon.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;&#xA;    Your browser does not support the video tag.&#xA;  &lt;/video&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&#xA;  &lt;figcaption style=&#34;font-size: 0.8em; color: gray;&#34;&gt;The animation shows the M67 isochrone in temperature–brightness and frequency diagrams (left). On the right, the internal structure of the stars is illustrated, with darker red indicating regions where oscillations are most sensitive to internal conditions. As the animation progresses—moving from less-massive to more-massive, or less-evolved to more-evolved stars—the grey convective envelope is seen deepening into the star. When the plateau frequencies are reached (marked in red on the left Frequency diagram), the base of the convective envelope aligns with the most sensitive region. The accompanying sound represents the oscillation frequencies translated into audible tones.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;What made this discovery possible is the unique nature of M67. Since its stars formed at the same time and have similar compositions, we can trace how seismic signals evolve with stellar evolution in a clean, controlled way.&#xA;&#xA;Our findings show that small separations still carry valuable information in evolved stars—and when combined with large separations, they can improve mass and age estimates well beyond the main sequence.&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;These results have been published in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; (April 10, 2025 issue).&lt;/strong&gt; 📖 Read the full paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-025-08&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asteroseismology of M67: Seismic Characterisation Across Evolutionary Phases</title>
      <link>https://claudiarreyes.github.io/post/m67/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 17:51:04 +1100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://claudiarreyes.github.io/post/m67/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ensemble asteroseismology has revolutionized our ability to empirically link observed seismic properties to fundamental stellar parameters. Star clusters, with their uniform metallicity, distance, and age, provide an ideal environment for refining these relations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we present the first asteroseismic analysis of M67 that spans its full evolutionary sequence, from subgiants to core helium-burning red giants, including a yellow straggler.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&#xA;  &lt;img src=&#34;https://claudiarreyes.github.io/images/psd.png&#34; alt=&#34;M67 stars examples&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;figcaption style=&#34;font-size: 0.8em; color: gray;&#34;&gt;Examples of the characteristic &#34;near Gaussian&#34;-shaped excess power observed in the power spectra of M67 stars from near the tip of the red-giant&#xA;branch (EPIC 211376143) to the subgiant branch (EPIC 211414203). The yellow curves represent the smoothed power spectrum, the white area represents the&#xA;portion of the spectrum where the excess power is located, and the red vertical lines indicate the frequency of maximum power, 𝜈&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;strong&gt;Kepler/K2&lt;/strong&gt; data, we measure seismic surface gravity, examine the potential role of core magnetic fields, and derive an empirical expression for the &lt;strong&gt;seismic surface term&lt;/strong&gt;. We also extend the analysis of the asymptotic phase term &lt;strong&gt;ɛ&lt;/strong&gt; to evolutionary stages previously unexplored in detail.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isochrone Fitting of M67 in the Gaia Era</title>
      <link>https://claudiarreyes.github.io/post/isochrone/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 16:39:31 +1100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://claudiarreyes.github.io/post/isochrone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Gaia mission has transformed our understanding of open clusters by significantly reducing scatter in colour-magnitude diagrams (CMDs). This improvement allows for more precise stellar modelling, making M67 an ideal test case.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Using Gaia’s refined CMD, we developed new stellar models that avoid common simplifications in 1D modelling, such as &lt;strong&gt;mass-independent core overshooting&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;constant mixing length parameter&lt;/strong&gt;. This approach led to an isochrone tailored specifically for M67, now available for download.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Machine Learning Approach to Vetting Δν</title>
      <link>https://claudiarreyes.github.io/post/vetting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://claudiarreyes.github.io/post/vetting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Asteroseismology provides precise measurements of stellar properties, making it a powerful tool for large-scale stellar studies. Two key parameters, ν&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt; (the frequency of maximum acoustic power) and Δν (the frequency separation between oscillation modes), are commonly used to estimate mass and radius. While automated methods can extract these values from power spectra, ensuring their accuracy typically requires manual vetting or strict filtering criteria.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this project we tested the performance of a neural network classifier designed to automate the vetting process for Δν. By incorporating multiple features used in visual inspections, the model achieves 95% accuracy in identifying reliable measurements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
